Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station Records 1972.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station Records
Bulk, 1888-1920
1882-1950
1972.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
28.0 Linear feet
The records of the Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station provide information on one of the oldest agricultural experiment and research stations in the United States. The records provide substantial information on the early years of the Experiment Station from 1888 to 1920. The majority of the records consist of correspondence to and from the executive and administrative staff of the station and local farmers and business organizations interested in obtaining information about the station's experiments and research findings.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Storrs Agricultural Experiement Station provide information on one of the oldest agricultural experiment and research stations in the United States. The records provide substantial information on the early years of the Experiment Station from 1888 to 1920.
The records provide valuable insight into the relations between the station and the farming communities in Connecticut, the interactions between agricultural stations and the relationship of the station to the state and federal government. The records also describe the agricultural problems of the times, the solutions and suggestions that were offered, and many of the farming implements and methods that were used in Connecticut during the period covered by the materials.
The records span the first sixty years of the experiment station's history (1888-1950), but the bulk of the records cover the period from 1888-1920. The majority of the records consist of correspondence to and from the executive and administrative staff of the station and local farmers and business organizations interested in obtaining information about the station's experiments and research findings. Significant correspondents include: W. O. Atwater, W. H. Leslie, F. E. Singleton, Clarence Atkins, Fred Chadwick, C. S. Phelps and W. B. Young. The records also contain detailed records of the station's financial condition from 1888 to 1899. The records do not contain the actual research findings or publications and bulletins of the Experiment Station.
History
The creation of an agricultural experiment station in Connecticut was first suggested by Professor Wilbur Olin Atwater of Wesleyan University in an address before the State Board of Agriculture in December 1873. Due to Atwater's persuasive powers, the Connecticut General Assembly appropriated $5,600 for the establishment of a temporary, two-year experiment station at Wesleyan University. The station, the first of its kind in America, was started in 1875 with Atwater as its director.
In March 1877, the General Assembly granted $5,000 annually for the creation of a permanent agricultural experiment station at Yale University, then the land grant college of Connecticut. The station was established at the Sheffield Scientific School of Yale in New Haven. Its first director was Professor Samuel Johnson of Yale.
In March 1877, Congress passed the Hatch Act which authorized to each state a grant of $15,000 for the creation of agricultural experiment stations in connection with the land grant colleges. Both Yale University and the Storrs Agricultural School, created in 1881, claimed the grant as the legitimate land grant college in Connecticut. The Storrs Agricultural School's claim was supported by the Connecticut State Grange. The Connecticut General Assembly settled the dispute by splitting the grant between the two claimants.
The Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station was formally established in April 1888, with Professor W. O. Atwater of Wesleyan University (Class of 1865) as its director. The purpose of the station was to conduct research and experiments to further agricultural progress. The results of investigations were published in the bulletins which were made available to Connecticut residents upon request. The station was directed from Wesleyan University. Field experiements were conducted at the Storrs Agricultural School, while laboratory experiements were conducted at the chemistry lab at Wesleyan University.
The General Assembly finally granted an annual appropriation of $1,800 for the Storrs Experiment Station in 1895. Professor Atwater remained the director until 1903 when he resigned and the station was reorganized under the sole control of the Storrs Agricultural College, completely severing its ties with Wesleyan University.
In 1912, the Connecticut Agricultural School at Yale and the Storrs Experiment Station were joined under the direction of Dr. E. H. Jenkins of Yale. The purpose of this joint directorship was to ensure harmony of purpose and to prevent duplication of effort. Professor Jenkins remained the director of the station until 1922, when he was replaced by Professor William L. Slate, Jr., a Professor of Agronomy at the Connecticut Agricultural School. Professor Slate served as director until 1949. Members of the Station staff devoted the majority of their time to research while others taught and conducted research depending upon the needs of the Station, In 1925, Congress passed the Purnell Act which granted to Connecticut an annual sum of $60,000 in support of its two experiment stations. The Connecticut Agricultural School specialized primarily in plant work, while the Storrs Experiment Station focused on animal industry.
The achievements of the Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station during its first fifty years of existence were notable. Investigations were conducted in numerous areas such as poultry disease and breeding, animal parasites, calf-feeding, pasture management and other subjects. The station was the first to describe and classify the bacteria of milk and milk products. It contributed greatly to the knowledge of the role of legumes in soil fertility, helped to establish practices for the feeding and management of dairy cattle and it worked out the correct practices for the incubation of eggs. Measures for controlling stomach worm in sheep were also developed at the Station.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Custodial History
The records of the Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station were given to the Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station by the Olin Library of Wesleyan University on 28 June 1966. The records were then transferred to the University of Connecticut Library Special Collections Department. In 1973, the records were removed from Special Collections due to lack of storage space and placed in the College of Agriculture vault.
Provenance and Acquisition
The records were transferred from the College of Agriculture to the University Archives in 1981.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Storrs Agricultural College.; Archives.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Reports.; University of Connecticut.
- Series I: An Inventory, 1882, 1888-1920, 1924, 1933-1947; 22.05 Linear feet
  Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture--Connecticut.; Agriculture—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Agriculture.; Financial Records.; Ledgers.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)-- Education.; Storrs (Conn.)--Education--Universities and colleges.; Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; Storrs, Conn.; University of Connecticut--History.; University of Connecticut.
  - Correspondence, ephemera, fliers, notes, administrative records, transcripts, financial records, manuscripts, 1897, 1901-1905, 1907-1909, 1911, 1913, 1914, 1916, 1917, 1919, 1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized A-B (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from companies and organizations: A.B. Ansbacher and Co.; Ansbacher Insecticide Co, Inc.; American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Coal Products Company; American Cooperative Creameries Association; American Express Company; American Farm-Management Association; American Flax Fibre & Linen Corp.; American Milling Company; American Hardware Corporation.
    Correspondence to and from individuals: Pres. Charles Lewis Beach, Charles M. Jarvis, Pres. Rufus W. Stimson, L.A. Prof. Clinton, Francis G. Benedict, James S. Judd, Frank Avery, Prof. H.J. Baker, Prof. William L. Slate, E.H. Jenkins, Dir. H.J. Baker.
    Correspondence with farms and experiment stations: Middletown, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station; Vermont Agricultural Experiment Station (Burlington, VT.); Valentine Farm; Snow Farm; Whitney Farm.
    Agricultural subjects discussed in correspondence: sulfate of ammonia as pesticide; camembert cheese (Charles M. Jarvis); shropshire sheep; winter vetch; alfalfa hay; poultry testing; crop planting; pigs; white pine blister; model farms.
    Fliers, publications, and Ephemera on: "The Fourth Annual Meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Agricultural Teaching, November 11, 1913" (schedule of events); "Potato Scab and its Prevention" (flier); "Farm Estimate for quarter July-Sept. 1908;" "Practical Agriculture."
    General Subjects, Storrs, Connecticut, University of Connecticut, University of Connecticut History, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, Storrs Agricultural School.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture--Connecticut.; Middletown (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.); University of Connecticut--History.
  - Correspondence, notes, postcards, 1893, 1896-1903, 1905, 1907-1913, 1916, 1918-1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized B-C (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: A.L. Benedict, inventor of "Benedict's Celebrated Rolling Window Screens for the Exclusion of Insects;" Prof. L.A. Clinton; Fred L. Belden; Peaceful Nook Farm, Huckleberry Hills (New Canaan, CT); Dr. F.G. Benedict; Prof. W.O. Atwater; A.P. Bryant; Davol Rubber Co.; Melvin Brandow; Title Insurance Company; Fred Koenig; H.C. Burrington; A.I. Bush, Attorney at Law; Greenwich High School; Ontario Agricultural College (Guelph, Canada); Ontario Veterinary College; Dominion of Canada Department of Agriculture; "The Canadian Horticulturalist" (publication); United States Department of Agriculture, Washington, D.C.; U.S. Senate Committee on Agriculture and Forestry; Middletown, CT, Experiment Station.
    Agricultural Subjects in correspondence: pesticide use; San Jose Scale insects; metabolism experiments--carbon content; alcohol experimentation; fertilizers; cultivation of soy beans; Bordeaux Mixture (for fighting Blight); Chestnut Blight; leaf-miners; soil testing; alfalfa cultivation.
    General Subjects: Storrs Agricultural School, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, Middletown Experiment Station, Storrs, CT, University of Connecticut History.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)--Universities and colleges.; Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; University of Connecticut--History.
  - Correspondence, financial records, publications, legal documents, ephemera, 1889, 1894, 1896-1901, 1904-1914, 1917-1918, 1920, 1924; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized C-D (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: Professor W.L. Slate; Alfred Cochran; Thomas M. Cochrane; The Core Brass Manufacturing Company; The Coe Mortimer Company, Importers of Genuine Peruvian Guano, Manufacturers of E. Frank Coe's High Grade Fertilizers; Connecticut Board of Agriculture; Prof. L.A. Clinton; State Comptroller's Office (Thompson S. Grant, Comptroller; T.D. Bradstreet, Comptroller); "Corn" Magazine; Correspondence Insititute of America; Irving G. Davis; Corbin Screw Corporation.
    Publications: "Legislative Bulletin," Friday, March 3, 1899, and Tuesday, March 7, 1899; "An Act Concerning the State Board of Agriculture;" "Prospectus: Farmers' Institutes by the Connecticut State Board of Agriculture, in Cooperation with the State and Storres Experiment Stations for 1898-1899; Farmers' Convention Program (ephemera); "Handbook of Fairs and Dates: Issued by the State Board of Agriculture July 1, 1917."
    Agricultural subjects in correspondence: plant fertilization, pigeons, tobacco cultivation, bacteria for fertilization of crops, potato cultivation, manure application to crops, white leghorns, denatured alcohol, dairy bacteriology, decorative grasses, orchard cultivation, San Jose Scale insects.
    General Subjects: Storrs Agricultural School, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, University of Connecticut History.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture—Connecticut.; Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; University of Connecticut--History.
  - Correspondence, postcards, posters, notes, financial records, legal documents, 1897-1898, 1903, 1906-1911, 1913-1918, 1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized E-G (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: The E.C. Brown Company, Manufacturers of Pumps; E.D. Chittenden Company; E.D. Cummings; E.L. Freeman & Sons, Stationers, Printers, Binders; Meadow Brook Farm; Echo Farm, Litchfield, Connecticut; Electric Boat Company, Groton, CT; Edison Manufacturing Company; Eimer and Amend, Manufacturers and Importers of Chemicals and Chemical Apparatus; Du Pont; Federal Chemical Company; Federation of Jewish Farmers of America; Travelers Insurance Company; Maple Shade Farm; Pres. Charles Lewis Beach; Gardner Advertising Company, Essex, CT; James Gould Company.
    Agricultural and experimental subjects discussed in correspondence include: seed oats, seed potatoes, onion seed, suitable and unsuitable crops for cow pastures, weevils, Rhode Island Red eggs, potato beetles, Kjeldahl Flasks, thermometers, preparing soil with dynamite (for tree stump removal), barometers, ether, ground phosphate rock, alfalfa cultivation.
    Items regarding events: "New England Farm and Business Conference: Under the Auspices the Eastern States Agricultural and Industrial Exposition, Inc.: Held in Springfield, Mass., Sept. 15 and 16, 1916" (Poster); "Eastern States Exposition and Dairy Show, 1913."
    General Subjects: Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, Storrs Agricultural School, University of Connecticut History.
  - Correspondence, postcards, notes, ephemera, 1896-1902, 1904, 1907-1913, 1915; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized G-H (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: Grasselli Chemical Company; Prof. L.A. Clinton; Dr. Charles B. Graves, M.D.; F.W. Gray; C.D. Jarvis; W.O. Atwater; Great Britain Royal Agricultural Society; Yorkshire College; Cardiff Public Libraries; Board of Agriculture and Fisheries; Board of Agriculture for Scotland; J. Stillwell Grover; Hammond, Knowlton & Co., Silk Manufacturers; Pope Manufacturing Company, automobile manufacturer of Hartford, Conn.; Pres. R.W. Stimson; Holstein-Friesian Association of America; Russell Manufacturing Co.; L.D. Huff; D.Y. Hallock & Sons; Harder Manufacturing Company; Hoffmann, Ahlers & Co.; Hall Camera Co.; Pennsylvania Department of Agriculture; Hammond Typewriter Company; Pequot Poultry Farm; Melrose Castle Farm.
    Agricultural subjects in correspondence include: sulphuric acid, arsenate of lead (as insecticide), San Jose Scale insects, "Miscible oil for Spraying Purposes" (pesticide), treating peach trees and cherry trees against pests, Bordeaux Mixture (pesticide), production of Camembert Cheese, soluble oil (pesticide), poison content of carrots, peas and beans, Oyster Shell Scale (pest), milk-producing goats, dairy bacteria.
    Items related to Agricultural Events: "Horticultural Society of New York International Conference on Plant Hardiness and Acclimatization" schedule of events (ephemera).
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture--Connecticut.; Connecticut Agricultural College.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; University of Connecticut--History.; University of Connecticut.
  - Correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, legal documents, notes, 1893, 1895-1897, 1903-1904, 1908-1909, 1911-1912, 1915-1918, 1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized I-P (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: University of Illinois; Iowa State University, Division of Veterinary Medicine (Ames, Iowa); Prof. L.A. Clinton; Second Congregational Church of Mansfield; Odd Fellows' Home of Connecticut; Central Vermont Railway Company; Prof. W.L. Slate; Hampden County (Mass.) Improvement League; State of Connecticut Board of Agriculture; Pres. Charles Lewis Beach; C.D. Jarvis; State Normal School of California; Leeds & Northrop Company; H.F. Judkins; Kentucky Tobacco Product Co.; Col. Charles Maples Jarvis; Herbert K. Job, State Ornithologist of Connecticut; R. Hart Geer; Horner's Zoological Arena: Wild Animal Importers; John B. Doolin, State Game and Fish Warden, Oklahoma; Chemical Laboratory, Wesleyan University; Benjamin Franklin Koons.
    Agricultural topics discussed in correspondence include: nitrate of soda, plant fertilizer, leaf blight, potato blight, creation of cheese, soluble oil (pesticide), arsenate of lead (pesticide), electrical measuring instruments, poultry manure, millet, fertilizing potatoes, quail disease.
    Publications and Manuscripts: Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station Bulletin no. 27, December, 1903 (fragment); "Problems in Fruit Growing" (Manuscript).
    General Subjects: Storrs Agricultural School, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, University of Connecticut History, Storrs, Connecticut History.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture--Connecticut.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)--Universities and colleges.; Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; University of Connecticut--History.; University of Connecticut.
  - Correspondence, financial records, ephemera, publications, postcards, 1895-1896, 1902-1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized L-M (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: Prof. L.A. Clinton; Fairlea Farm, Orange, CT; Maple Ridge Farm; U.S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C.; American Witch-Hazel Company, Charles C. Dickinson, Pres.; Town of Southington, CT; Loyal Protective Insurance Co.; Crescent Farm; Lowell Farms; New London County Improvement League; Prof. W.L. Slate; Curtis Publishing Company; Prof. A.G. Gulley; Illinois Metals Co.; Hatch Experiment Station, Massachusetts; Massachusetts Board of Agriculture; Michigan Agricultural College; Minnesota Agricultural Experiment Station; Dr. Conn; City of St. Louis Health Department; Montana State Board of Horticulture; Ohio State University; North Carolina Agricultural Experiment Station; Ohio Agricultural Experiment Station; University of Pennsylvania; Chester D. Jarvis; Moss Bros. Roller Coasters; Charles H. Moss; Morris European and American Express Co.; Litchfield Electric Light Corp.; Maryland Agricultural College; Massachusetts Institute of Technology; Prof. W.L. Slate.
    Agricultural Subjects discussed in correspondence include: raising cattle, crop rotation, crop fertilization and cultivation, fruit cultivation, harvesting corn and alfalfa, dairy cows, Canada peas, Army Worms, tobacco cultivation, cow peas, potatoes, San Jose scale insects, Maltese goats, dodder (parasitic plant), bacteria.
    Publications and ephemera: "Home Nature-Study Course, Cornell University," December 1903, discussing chickadees, snowstorms and egg production (correspondence course publication); Schedule for "Second Annual New England Conference on Rural Progress--Massachusetts State Board of Agriculture, March 5, 6, 1908" (ephemera).
    General Subjects include: Storrs Agricultural School, Agricultural Colleges and Schools, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, Agricultural Experiment Stations, United States, University of Connecticut History.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural colleges—Connecticut—History.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture—Connecticut.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)--Universities and colleges.; Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; University of Connecticut--History.
  - Correspondence, financial records, publications, photographs, ephemera, 1888, 1895-1898, 1902, 1904-1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized M-P (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: Correspondence to and from: Maine Agricultural Experiment Station; Journal of Agricultural Research; A.W. Buchanan; Prof. W.O. Atwater; Pres. B.F. Koons; Henry C. Miles; George K. Nason, Dealer in Lumber, Coal, Lime, Cement, Windows, Doors, Blinds, Mouldings, and Builders' Supplies, Est. 1862; Prof. L.A. Clinton; Prof. W.A. Stocking, Cornell University; Prof. C.L. Beach; Cornell Experiment Station; New Jersey Agricultural Experiment Station; Syracuse University; Natchaug Grange; New England Corn Exposition; Massachusetts Agricultural College; Prof. W.D. Hurd; American Breeders' Association; New Zealand Department of Agriculture, Commerce, and Tourists, Wellington, NZ; Gladys F. Ogden, Fortland Farm, Stamford, CT; Huntsville Improvement Club, Huntsville, Utah; Ohio State University; Ohio Agricultural Experiment Station; Prof. W.L. Slate; Wing and Evans, Inc., Agent for the Solvay Process Co., Manufacturer of Soda, Detroit, Michigan; Oregon Agricultural Experiment Station; Greene County Farm Bureau, Xenia, Ohio; James B. Olcott; Prof. C.A. Zavitz; Ontario Department of Agriculture, Guelph; Pennsylvania State College; Pelton & King, Printers and Binders; Central Vermont Railroad; Rhode Island Agricultural Experiment Station.
    Agricultural topics discussed in correspondence include: miscible oil, soluble oil, scalecide, poultry husbandry, pomology, potato culture, potato grubs, corn cribs, sulphuric acid as herbicide, grass culture.
    Publications and ephemera: "New York State Fruit Growers' Association" newsletter, Jan. 26, 1906; program for the "Twenty-fourth Annual Meeting of the Ontario Agricultural and Experimental Union, Dec. 8,9, 1902" (ephemera).
    General Subjects include: Storrs Agricultural School, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, Agricultural Experiment Stations, United States, University of Connecticut History.
    Agricultural colleges—Connecticut.; Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Agriculture--Connecticut.; Agriculture--Study and teaching.; Connecticut--Agriculture.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)—Agriculture.; Storrs (Conn.)—Education--Universities and colleges.; University of Connecticut--History.
  - Correspondence, notes, photographs, financial records, preliminary sketches, postcards, 1888-1890, 1892-1907, 1910-1914, 1916, 1918, 1920; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, alphabetized P-V (Box 9)